Mouna! Mouna!
莫那…莫那…
Bakan,
why does Mouna need so many matches?
巴岡，莫那幹嘛一直在買火柴？
Who knows?
誰知道…
Had any meat, my boy?
有沒有吃肉呀？
Have a drink!
喝杯酒吧！
Father! Father!
父親…父親！
Father, can we slaughter a cow?
父親…再殺頭牛吧！
Not enough to eat?
不夠吃嗎？
It's enough, but we haven't had beef
for such a long time
夠！可是大家好久沒吃牛肉了…
Do it then
…那就殺吧！
Let's slaughter a cow!
再殺一頭牛啊！
Hooray! Let's slaughter a cow!
好啊！頭目…再殺一頭牛唷！
Baso, grab it!
巴索…抓好…
Grab its legs!
扳牠的腳…
Come on!
快點！
I've cut off the head
of the Japanese Governor-general
日本總督的頭被我拿下來了…
Wow! What a party!
哇！這麼熱鬧啊…
Sir Yoshimura
吉村大人…
Whose wedding day is it?
今天又是誰結婚啊？
It's Watan and Lubi's
是瓦旦和露比結婚…
Come! Have a drink with us, sir
來！大人，你也來杯小米酒吧！
No
不要！
No -Come on, have a drink
-不要！
-來啦，一起喝嘛！
No way
不要啦…
I don't drink the wine with your nasty saliva in it
我才不喝這種用口水做的髒酒！
Come on, have a drink
-I told you that I don't want to
-來啦，喝嘛！
-跟你講不要…
Your hand is all dirty with blood
小心你手上的血…
I invited you with good will
-You son-of-a-bitch!
-我這麼好意請你…
-你這傢伙…
You've soiled me with blood!
看你把我弄得都是血了…
I offered you a drink and you hit me?
請你喝酒，你怎麼打人呢？
I'll beat you into senses!
不明白我打到你明白！
Stop!
-I don't need to reason with a savage
-不要打了…
-我還聽生蕃講理？
What is it? Let's go look!
怎麼了？…過去看看！
Hurry up!
快點…
I know what you said just now
with a boar's head in your hand
你提豬頭喊什麼蕃話我聽不懂嗎？
Out of my way!
Say it again in Japanese if you dare
讓開…有本事你用日語講一遍啊…
Say it again!
你再講一遍啊！
Get out of my way! -I dare you!
-讓開…
-你敢不敢講啊？
Come on, guys!
大家過去！
Faster!
跑快一點！
Tado!
達多…
Baso, kill him!
巴索…打死他…
I'm holding down his feet! Beat him up!
我抓住他的腳了，你們用力打！
I'm holding down his feet again!
我又抓住他的腳了…
Stop! All of you!
住手！…通通住手！
What is it? What the hell?
怎麼會這樣？搞什麼東西呀？
Let me cut off this pig head of yours!
看我砍下你這顆豬頭…
Stop! Stop! Yoshi..
不要打了…不要打了…吉…
Yoshimura
吉村…
You're in big trouble
你們完蛋了…
You have the nerve to beat me up
-Let's kill him!
竟然敢打我！
殺了他！
Shut your mouth!
你閉嘴！
Excuse us! Let us through!
借過…借過…
I'll kill all you Mehebu clansmen
…我一定要殺光你們馬赫坡！
I'll kill you all
…我一定會殺光你們馬赫坡！
Let's do it, Father,
before the Japanese kill us all
父親，先動手吧！
他們不會放過我們的！
Why the hell did you provoke him
when you knew he'd kill us all?
你明知道他們不會放過我們
你還要去惹他？
You're nothing but a bunch of hounds
你們這群只懂追獵…
that can only chase and hunt
and know nothing of self-restraint
不懂控制的獵犬！
How much longer do I have to put up with you?
我要忍耐你們到什麼時侯？
Out of my way!
讓開…讓開…
Now you're here to bribe me with wine?
現在才想到拿酒來求我？
It's too late
來不及了！
I've filed the report on the case
of you beating up a police officer
毆打巡查的案子我已經呈報上去了
Tell you something..
告訴你…
This time I'll destroy your clan
我一定要毀了你們整個部落！
Yoshimura..
吉村…
I, Mouna Rudo, come here to
apologize to you personally
我莫那魯道親自來跟你道歉
Stop being so arrogant
你別太不給臉…
Who do you think you are?
莫那魯道又怎樣！
You think you're still a chief?
你還像個頭目嗎？
You can't even control your own sons
連自己的兒子都管不好
I don't think you're qualified
to be a chief anymore
還有資格當頭目？
Get out!
出去！出去！
Who the hell let you in?
誰跟你說可以進來的
Get the hell out!
都給我滾出去！
I don't want to see your faces again
我不要再看到你們…
Go home and rot!
回家等死吧！
Hey! Why did you do that to him?
-Shut up!
喂！你們幹嘛打他呢？
閉嘴！
I couldn't sleep last night because of a mosquito
被一隻蚊子搞到整晚睡不著！
Really? I'll see to it
是喔，那我再去了解一下…
Mr. Hanaoka!
花岡先生
Yes?
是！
May I know which clan you grew up in?
請問你是哪一個蕃社長大的？
Gungu Clan
荷戈社！
And your original name?
本名呢？
Dakis Nawi
…達奇斯那威
達奇斯那威…
We have another savage policeman
named Hanoka Ichiro
我們還有個叫花岡一郎的蕃人警察
He is the highest educated policemen here
是所有山地警察中學歷最高的
What are you doing this afternoon?
…你下午有事要忙嗎？
I'm going home for some private matter
…我等一下有事情需要回家一趟
I was to ask you
to patrol all the savage clans with us
原本想請你陪我到各蕃社去視察
and tell me the relationships among them all
順便幫我介紹各蕃社的關係…
Come with us! -No, it's alright
-你先陪我們去嘛！
-沒關係…！
It's alright
沒關係的！
Do whatever you need to do
你先去辦你的事吧！
It's alright
沒關係！
Kabasawa will go with us -Yes
-樺澤會和我們去！
-是的！
He knows the savages well too
他也是個蕃通！
Yoshimura has reported
Tado's case to the substation
吉村已經把達多的案子…
上報到分室來了！
I can't believe this Yoshimura
這個吉村也真是的…
Chief Mouna apologized to him personally
莫那頭目都親自去道歉了
Why did he insist on filing the case?
怎麼還硬要把案子往上送！
Yoshimura and Sugiura are not the same
as Kojima after all
吉村和衫浦，畢竟不是小島
They will never try to understand our people
是不會花心思去了解族人
If Kojima were living in Mehebu
there wouldn't be so much trouble
如果小島在馬赫坡的話…
這事就算發生，也不會這麼嚴重
Since I was very little
從小到大…
I've always been scared of Chief Mouna
我一看到莫那頭目都會害怕
It looks as if underneath his mantle
he's always gripping his machete
總覺得他藏在披風裡的手
ready to draw it to kill anytime
是隨時握著刀準備獵殺的！
He's no ordinary man
不能小看他…
He's impossible to be tamed
他是不可能被馴服的！
It must be difficult for him to torn between
the expectations of his fellow tribesmen
夾在族人期望和日本人威脅之間
and the intimidation of the Japanese
生活是很痛苦的！
Aren't we living like that as well?
我們兩個不也是這樣子嗎？
We don't want to be savages
…不想當野蠻人
but however hard
we try to dress up like the Japanese
但不管怎麼努力裝扮
we'll always be seen as uncivilized people
也改變不了這張不被文明認同的臉
We've lived like this for 20 years
已經忍了二十年了
Another 20 years won't be impossible
就再忍個二十年吧！
By the time our children grow up
等我們的孩子長大…
maybe we will have changed forever
the savage image of ours
或許就能徹底改變我們的野蠻形象
Do we still have the chance?
忍得了嗎？
Mehebu Clan may be wiped out soon
馬赫坡就要被趕盡殺絕了…
Father, let's fight the Japanese
父親…和日本人拚了吧！
Ouch! It hurts! -You dumb ass!
-燙…好燙啊…
-混帳東西！
Father, don't be mad!
父親…不要生氣…
Father! -You never learn!
-父親…父親…
-講不聽！
Enough! -You moron!
-好了…夠了啦…
-混帳東西！
Oh no! How come..
糟糕…怎麼…
It's the temporary bamboo bridge
that the savages used in the past
那是蕃人以前使用的竹便橋
It's ugly and insecure,
又醜又不堅固
but they keep walking over it
可是他們還老是要走那邊…
I'll tear it down sooner or later
哪天我直接把它給拆了！
But it saves them lots of time
if they walk over it to fetch water or to the field
其實他們提水或是到田裡…
都還是走那邊比較方便呀！
Look! This wire bridge is strong and firm
你看這鐵線橋做得這麼堅固！
Tado?
達多…
This young man is Tado Mouna
這個年輕人叫達多莫那
the eldest son of the Mehebu chief Mouna Rudo
是馬赫坡社頭目莫那魯道的長子
But he saw us without saying anything
Is there anything wrong with him?
他見到我們怎麼沒有任何表示？
是不是有什麼問題？
No, it's a habit of the savages
-It's not a very good habit
沒事！這是蕃人的習慣！
這不是很好的習慣！
Oh well, they're savages after all
…因為他們是生蕃嘛！
Can you stop talking about them like that?
你可以不要一直用這種口氣嗎？
Sugiura! -Welcome, sirs
-衫浦…
-主任、課長，歡迎！
This is Officer Sugiura
這位是衫浦巡查…
This way please
請往這邊走！
You should've informed me
before you came here, sir
課長要來怎麼不先通知呢？
I could've asked those savages
to welcome you with dances
我可以叫這些蕃人來跳舞歡迎啊！
No need for that
不用麻煩了…
We're only showing our hospitality
哎呀！課長怎麼這樣客氣呀！
Chief Mouna!
莫那頭目…
What?
幹嘛？
Chief Mouna,
莫那頭目…
can you tell me something about Japan?
跟我說說日本內地的事吧！
I know you've been there before
我知道你去過日本！
They have armies, cannons, machineguns
…日本有軍隊、大砲和機關槍…
airplanes and large steamers in Japan
飛機和大輪船…
There are more Japanese people
than the tree leaves in the forest
日本人比森林的樹葉還要繁密
than the pebbles in Jhuoshuei River
比濁水溪的石頭還多！
I know why you're asking me this
我也知道你問這些…
You don't really want to know Japan
並不是真的想知道那裡的事
All you want is to remind me
how powerful the Japanese are
你只是要提醒我日本有多厲害而已
Don't worry. I'll never forget
你放心吧！我不會忘記的！
Humph! You Japanese policemen
took us on the ship for days to Japan
哼！你們這些日本警察…
帶我們坐好幾天的船去日本
but all they showed us
were airplanes and cannons
卻只讓我們看飛機、大砲…
However, the policemen in Japan
不過…
were much nicer and kinder
than those of you here
那邊的警察比你們山地警察好多了
They feared we'd revolt against them
so they tried their best to befriend us
他們擔心反抗，想盡辦法對我們好
But those of you here in the mountains
但是你們這些山地日本警察
always provoke us so much
that I want to hunt your heads
卻總是壞得讓我想出草！
Chief Mouna, I'm still a Seediq
莫那頭目，我還是一個賽德克啊！
Although I'm now a Japanese policeman
雖然我是日本警察
I never forget
that the same blood runs in our veins
但我沒忘記我和你們流著一樣的血…
Dakis, when you die
are you entering a Japanese shrine?
達奇斯…
你將來要進日本人的神社？
Or the heavenly home of our ancestors?
還是我們祖靈的家？
I heard that..
…我聽說了
in the school for savage children
you beat up our kids like the Japanese do
你在蕃童教育所裡…
像日本人一樣地打著我們的孩子！
I beat them up because I don't want
the Japanese to look down on them
我打他們是希望…
…希望他們不要被日本人瞧不起！
You graduated from Normal School
你師範學校畢業
You're more highly-educated
than any other Japanese policemen
學歷比其他的日本警察還高
But how come you get the lowest salary?
為什麼你領的薪水是最低的？
Don't the Japanese look down on you already?
日本人瞧得起你嗎？
Beating up your own people makes them
look down on you even more
…自己打自己才會讓人瞧不起！
During our stay in Japan
以前去日本觀光的時侯
the Japanese knew all of us chiefs
from different clans hated one another
日本人明知道我們族群間有仇恨…
but they made us sit together
at the dining table deliberately
還故意安排我們坐在一起吃飯
We were glaring at one another
all the time while we were eating
讓我們每個人邊吃飯邊瞪著對方
intending to draw our machetes and kill
恨不得馬上拔刀殺了對方！
Humph! The Japanese are good at these things
哼，這些日本人就是懂這個…
Chief, is it so bad to be ruled by the Japanese?
頭目，被日本統治不好嗎？
At least we're leading a civilized life
我們現在文明的過生活
We have schools and post offices
有教育所，有郵局
and we don't have to survive
by hunting savagely anymore
不必再像從前一樣…
得靠野蠻的獵殺才能生存
Is it so bad to be ruled by the Japanese?
…被日本人統治不好嗎？
Is it so good to be ruled by them?
被日本人統治好嗎？
Our men are forced to bend over
to carry logs on our backs
男人被迫彎腰搬木頭
and our women have to kneel down
to serve and pour wine
女人被迫跪著幫傭陪酒
And all the money ends up
in the pockets of the Japanese policemen
該領的錢全進了日本警察的口袋
I'm a chief
我這個當頭目的…
but all I can do is get drunk
and pretend I see nothing and hear nothing
除了每天醉酒假裝看不見、聽不見
What else can I do?
還能怎麼樣？
Post offices? Stores? Schools?
郵局？商店？學校？
Do any of those things
make our lives easier and better?
什麼時侯讓族人的生活過得更好？
Instead,
we're made to see how impoverished we are
反倒讓他們看見自己有多貧窮了！
Chief, can't we bear it for another 20 years?
頭目…
我們再忍個二十年好嗎？
In 20 years, there will be no Seediq
and there will be no hunting ground
再二十年就不是賽德克！
就沒有獵場！
All our children will have turned Japanese
孩子全都是日本人了！
Chief Mouna,
…莫那頭目…
have you made up your mind to do it?
你真的要幹了嗎？
Chief Mouna?
莫那頭目…
About Yoshimura... -I'm old
-毆打吉村的事…
-我已經老了…
Don't worry
放心吧！
The Japanese are far too powerful
日本人這麼厲害
I won't go against them
我不敢怎樣的…
Go home
你回去吧！
This is the hunting ground
that belongs to me only
這裡是我一個人的獵場…
Get lost
你走開！
Chief... -Get lost!
-頭目…
-走開！
Dakis, have a drink
達奇斯…喝酒吧！
Go home and get yourself dead-drunk
回家以後喝它個大醉吧！
We can't drink anymore
不能再喝了…
We already... -Drink!
-我們已經…
-喝吧！
The millet wine that we make
我們釀的酒…
can set our people free
可以讓人無拘無束
making them sing and dance,
cry and laugh freely
讓人唱歌跳舞、哭笑隨性！
You'll see once you're drunk
大醉一場之後你就會懂了！
Go home now
回去吧！
Mouna!
莫那…
Father?
…父親…
Mouna, the tattoos on your face
are still so dark and clear
莫那！
你臉上的刺紋還是這麼的深黑…
You're indeed a Seediq Bale
你果然是一個賽德克巴萊！
You're a true hero
一個真正的英雄哪！
Mouna? Look at the lines on that rock
…莫那！
It split into half
when struck by the lightening, didn't it?
你看那巨石的線條…
是被雷光削開的吧！
In the dim light at dusk
the lightening splits a rock into half
昏黑的天色下…雷光削巨石…
What a beautiful sight!
多美麗的畫面啊！
Father?
父親…
I can't keep the intruders away
我阻止不了異族人…
(Ah, it's for real)
啊~真的啊！
(Here l am)
我來到這裡
(l used to guard these mountains
and forests bravely)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
(Oh yes, it's for real)
真的呀…是真的！
Mouna, let's sing
莫那…
來唱歌吧！
We haven't sung together for long
好久沒一起唱歌了！
(Reminisce the people from the past)
懷念過去的人們啊…
(Here l am)
我來到這裡
(l used to guard these mountains
and forests bravely)
我曾英勇守護的山林…
(These are our mountains)
這是我們的山唷…
(These are our creeks)
這是我們的溪唷…
(We're the true Seediq Bale)
我們是真正的賽德克巴萊唷…
(We go hunting in the mountains)
我們在山裡追獵…
(We share food in our clan)
我們在部落裡分享
(We fetch water from the creeks)
我們在溪流裡取水…
(l'm willing to give my life for these)
願我為此獻出生命…
(Oh, creek! Be quiet)
溪流啊！不要再吵了…
(Sisin babblers are singing)
祖靈鳥在唱歌了…
(Sing us a beautiful song please)
請唱首好聽的歌吧！
(Sing for our people)
為我們的族人唱…
(a song of our ancestral spirit)
來自祖靈的歌…
(l'm willing to give my life too)
願我也獻出生命！
(When the lightening rifts the rock)
巨石雷光下
(a rainbow appears)
彩虹出現了…
(and a proud man emerges)
一個驕傲的人走來了…
(Who is this man so proud?)
是誰如此驕傲啊？
(lt's your offspring)
是你的子孫啊…
(A Seediq Bale)
賽德克巴萊！
What?
什麼！
Tado Mouna became a hero before I did
達多怎麼比我先當上英雄了！
Those Japanese are outrageous
這些日本人實在太可惡了！
I can't believe they beat up someone
who offers them a drink
連請他喝酒都要被打…
A while ago..
上一次…
three girls from Boarung Clan
were asked to serve them drinks
波阿崙社有三個女孩被叫去陪酒
and they were raped
還被強暴！
Why couldn't Tado be a real hero
…達多既然想當英雄
and kill Yoshimura right on the spot?
怎麼不直接把吉村給殺了！
Kill him?
殺了他？
Don't you remember how my family died?
…我的家人怎麼死的？
難道你們忘了嗎？
My father killed only one Japanese man
我父親只殺了一個日本人
and they burned my whole family alive
我們全家人就被大火給活活燒死…
I was hiding in the woods watching
那時我躲在樹林裡…
without even blinking my eyes
可是連眼睛都沒眨一下…
So..
所以…
that's why we can't kill only one Japanese man
絕對不能只殺掉一個日本人…
We have to kill all of them to make a difference
一定要殺光所有的日本人才行！
Are you kidding me?
你在開玩笑嗎？
We wouldn't still be sitting here
if we could kill them all
如果殺得完的話
我們為什麼還要忍到現在？
Now the Mehebu chief Mouna Rudo
is driven to bay
因為今天馬赫坡的莫那魯道…
by that policeman from the lumberyard
被製材所的小警察逼上了絕路！
and the day after tomorrow on October 27th
is the big sports day
後天十月二十七日霧社舉行運動會…
By then, all the Japanese in Wushe
are going to gather in one place
到時霧社所有的日本人…
都會集合在一起…
Is it time already?
時侯真的到了嗎？
Father, there won't be a better chance
父親！等不到更好的機會了！
And we have no other choice
這是最後的路了…
We can't have the Japanese look down
on us anymore
不要再讓日本人看不起我們
We need to show them what we're made of
要讓他們知道我們也不是好惹的！
Let's fight them, Chief
頭目，和他們拚了吧！
Yeah! Let's fight them
對！跟他們拚了吧…
Young men..
年輕人…
I hate the Japanese no less than you do
我對日本人的仇恨
不會少於你們…
But do you realize that
只是你們知道行動之後…
we're going to die after all this
and all our people will be wiped out?
我們一定會死…甚至滅族嗎？
Our ancestors shed their blood
in exchange for our lives
我們的生命是祖先染血換來的
Now we're taking our children along
to the battlefield to shed blood
我們也要帶著子孫們一起染紅戰衣！
We're Seediq Bale, aren't we?
我們是賽德克巴萊呀！
Temu, does your father know you're here?
泰牧…
你父親知道你過來嗎？
My father told me that I should ask Chief Mouna
我父親告訴我…
請莫那頭目幫忙…
to help us youngsters get our faces tattooed
在孩子們的臉上作印記！
so that the ancestors' spirits
guarding the rainbow bridge
讓彩虹橋上的祖靈
will recognize us as the true Seediqs
永遠認得我們這些真正的賽德克…
Father?
父親…
If we want revenge,
it'd be the business of Mehebu Clan alone
如果說復仇，那是我馬赫坡的事
But if we're offering a blood sacrifice
to our ancestors
但是如果要血祭祖靈的話…
it will be the business of all the 12 clans
in Wushe
霧社十二個部落全部都要參加…
Keep it a secret before action
行動前先守住秘密！
We must tell none of the elders,
children or women in all these clans
所有部落裡的老人、小孩、女人
When did you..
-都不能知道…
-這是甚麼時侯…
I'm speaking here. Are you listening?
我講話…有沒有在聽啊？
Keep it a secret before action
行動前先守住秘密…
I knew Chief Mouna had a plan already
我就知道莫那頭目早有計劃…
What do you know?
It's your idea and your responsibility
你又知道什麼？你起的頭你負責…
Inform the chiefs of all the 12 clans
聯絡十二個血盟部落的頭目…
Tomorrow morning..
明天上午…
we're going to gather in Wushe
一起在霧社集合
and offer a blood sacrifice
…血祭祖靈！
Our ancestors' spirits..
祖靈們！
We're here for the guns. Sorry to disturb you
我們來取槍，無意打擾你們！
Boss.. -Welcome. This way please
-老闆…
-歡迎…裡面請…
Fill them up with salt
And give me ten boxes of matches
鹽…裝滿…火柴十盒…
Wow! Lots of things to buy, huh?
買這麼多？
Boss, we'll pay for it next time
老闆…這個先欠著吧？
On credit again?
又要欠錢？
Yes, we can -How much is it?
-可以的啦…
-老闆…這多少錢？
No, you can't!
不行不行！
Wait! You're buying all these on credit?
等一下…你們這些全部都要欠喔？
It's alright
沒關係啦…
It's alright? But you never pay me back!
沒關係…沒關係…你們有還過嗎？
Let's give them a hand
到外面幫忙！
That old drunkard Mouna Rudo
really can't take it anymore?
莫那魯道這老酒鬼真的忍不住了？
I'll ask the young men to get ready
before they all get dead drunk
我去召集年輕人準備了
要不然醉光就麻煩了
Young man, how dare you tell me these
年輕人…
你好大的膽子呀…
in front of the police station!
在駐在所前跟我說這些…
Good morning!
早安啊！
Pihu Sapu?
比荷沙波…
What the hell was he up to?
這小子在幹嘛？
That crazy boy spells nothing but trouble
整天瘋瘋癲癲的只會惹事…
But we'd be bored around here
without him, won't we?
不過…如果山上少了他
應該會很無趣吧！
You call making troubles interesting?
到處惹事叫有趣嗎？
Tado, look! Only the gun barrel is left
達多，你看…
都爛成這樣了！
No, I won't do it -Won't do it?
我不答應！
不答應？
Chief Dahdo..
塔道頭目
the chiefs of the other clans
have all agreed to join us
其他部落頭目都答應了
and everything is ready now
我們也都準備計劃好了
Fighting the Japanese will lead us to death only
和日本軍隊拚只有死路一條
We've had three chiefs in our family
that died of fighting the Japanese
我們家族三代頭目都為抗日而死
Now we've stooped to bring you kids up
今天…
to carry on the lifeline of our people
not to get killed on the battlefield
我們辛苦忍辱把你們這些孩子養大
是為了要保住族群命脈
不是要你們去求死的！
Chief... -We're not afraid of death
-頭目 -我們不怕死！
Even Chief Mouna agreed to do it
人家連莫那頭目都答應了！
Chief Dahdo, they'll laugh at us if you don't do it
塔道頭目…
你這樣人家會笑我們的
They can laugh at me for all I care
笑我怕死也沒關係
I'll never allow our Gungu Clan
to join the battle. Period
我就是不准我荷戈社參戰！
But Chief.. -Chief!
頭目…頭目…
頭目！
Are you going to be a hunter
forever without guns or hunting grounds?
難道你要永遠當一個…
沒有槍、沒有獵場的獵人嗎？
You have no tattoo on your face
Don't forget whom you're talking to
你這個沒有圖騰的孩子…
不要忘了你的身份！
What do we do now?
現在怎麼辦呢？
I can't stand that old man
真受不了這個老頭子…
No way
不可能！
I won't allow our young clansmen
我不會讓我們的年輕人
to sacrifice themselves in vain
with you maniacs
陪著你們這些瘋子去白白犧牲…
But.. -I won't let out this secret of yours
可是…
我不會把你們的秘密說出去的…
Go home
你回去吧！
You only show off your bravery
with those animal skulls now?
你現在只靠獸骨炫耀你的勇敢嗎？
Chief Walis, you once fought the Japanese
at Hakaw Supeitei
瓦力斯頭目…
當年在人止關
Where's your bravery now?
你對抗日本人的英勇哪裡去了？
Bravery? I gave it all to you long ago
英勇？
…我全部都已經留給你了！
Bring your women and children here
to our Paran Clan
把女人孩子帶過來我們巴蘭社吧！
to keep the bloodline of your clan
替你們部落留些人口…
A clan so big...with so many people..
這麼大的一個部落
這麼多的人…
What are you doing?
你們在幹嘛？
Hello, sir!
大人好！
Come closer
靠中間站一點…
Stop fooling around!
Go home and clean your places up
不要嘻皮笑臉，快回去整理環境！
Yes, sir
好
Go on!
快走！
Sorry
對不起…
Stay away, kids
那邊的小朋友讓開…
Okay, ready
好！那要拍囉！
One, two, three
一、二、三！
I'm not going in
我就送你們到這裡了！
Make me proud in tomorrow's games
明天加油喔…
Can you stay with us, Father?
父親也留下來嘛！
No, I can't. I have to go back before dark
不行…
父親再不回去，要天黑了…
You're spending the night here
Be a good boy, you hear?
晚上睡別人家裡要乖喔…
懂不懂？
See you then
那我走了！
Bye -Take care
再見！
小心慢走…
Let's go!
我們走吧！
Excuse me!
不好意思…
Mouna knows everything about battles
…莫那…
這傢伙確實懂得戰鬥…
But I'm old. I can't go with him
不過我已經老了，不能陪他去了…
But..
-But our Drodux Clan won't be absent in this
可是…
可是我們羅多夫是不會缺席的…
Do I have to say it again in Japanese?
…要我說日本話嗎？
Good morning!
早安…早安…
Pihu! What's wrong with you?
比荷！搞什麼啊你？
Pihu!
比荷…
Good morning!
早…安…
Why did you get all our hounds
to bark like crazy?
你幹嘛惹得我整個部落狗吠…
Chief Mouna, didn't you say
that you wouldn't do it?
莫那頭目，你不是說你不會幹嗎？
Do what? Who says I'm doing anything?
要幹什麼？…誰跟你說我要幹的？
Dakis, you're nothing
but a police dog wearing a collar
達奇斯…
你這隻戴著項圈的警犬…
Did your master send you here
as a persuader?
你的主人派你來勸降的嗎？
-Tado!
達多！
Dakis, you haven't answered
my question from last time
達奇斯…
你上次還沒有回答我
When you die,
are you entering a Japanese shrine
你將來要進日本人的神社
or the heavenly home of our ancestors?
還是我們賽德克祖靈的家？
Are you Dakis? Or Hanaoka Ichiro?
你是達奇斯？還是花岡一郎？
I'm a true Seediq tribesman. I am!
我是真正的賽德克！我是…
But...
-If you are, take off your uniform
-可是…
-是的話就換掉這身衣服
and offer blood sacrifice to our ancestors
with us tomorrow
明天和我們一起血祭祖靈！
You know well
how many soldiers the Japanese have
你又不是不知道日本軍隊有多少…
You're going to get killed for nothing
這麼做只不過是白白犧牲而已…
You told me the other day that there are
more Japanese people than..
你上次不是還說日本人比森林裡的…
There are more Japanese people
than the tree leaves in the forest
日本人比森林的樹葉還要繁密…
than the pebbles in Jhuoshuei River
比濁水溪裡的石頭還要多…
But my determination to fight them
is more adamant than Mt. Chilai
但我反抗的決心比奇萊山還要堅定！
If your civilization wants us to cringe
如果你的文明是叫我們卑躬屈膝
I'll show you the pride of savages
那我就帶你們看見野蠻的驕傲！
The true Seediq tribesmen
真正的賽德克…
Listen carefully, Dakis
達奇斯…
You being a Seediq descendant
who never tried to understand yourself
你這從來不想了解自己的子孫聽好…
A Seediq Bale can lose his body
賽德克巴萊可以輸去身體…
but he fights to keep his soul at all cost
但是一定要贏得靈魂！
A Seediq who loses his soul
輸去靈魂的賽德克…
will be forsaken by our ancestors' spirits
一定會遭到祖靈遺棄！
Do you understand..
你懂了嗎？
..my child?
…孩子啊！
There are over 130 guns
in the Wushe substation
…霧社分室裡有一百三十幾枝槍
and many boxes of ammunition too
還有好幾箱彈藥…
On the sports day tomorrow
明天運動會的時侯
Jiro...Dakis Nawi will be on duty
二郎…達奇斯那威值勤
I'll tell him everything beforehand
我會先跟他講好…
Father, will he betray us?
父親，他會不會跑去密告啊？
No, he won't
他不會的！
Can't believe all the gunpowder
I spent years collecting will go to waste
害我白白準備了那麼多年的火藥…
What is it, Pihu? -They're all cowards!
比荷，怎麼樣了？
都是些膽小鬼啦！
Chief, only six clans are willing to join us
頭目…
只有六個社願意參加
A little more than 300 men in all
-300 men?
人數也才三百多個人而已！
…三百人？
I tried so hard to persuade them
我一直講一直講…
I was so incensed that
I nearly drew my machete
講到我獵刀都快拔出來了
But they... -Take it easy
-可是他們…
-你放輕鬆…
It's quite enough to have 300. Go home quietly
Chief..
頭目…
三百個夠了…
全部都安安靜靜的離開
Don't get caught before action
-Chief..
-別還沒行動就被抓了…
-頭目…
Get out of here. All of you
出去…全部離開…
Get out!
出去！
(Why do men belittle women so?)
你們男人為何要這樣欺負女人…
(Don't forget all the pride you boast of)
別忘了所有你們自誇的驕傲
(comes from us women)
都是來自我們女人
(lt is us who weave your glory)
是我們女人為你們所編織的呀！
(lt is us women behind men's tattoos of bravery)
是女人成就了男人英勇的圖騰呀！
The sun..
太陽…
(l'm on my way)
我正在路上
(to the heavenly home of our ancestors)
我要走向祖靈之家了
(We'll be back as brothers)
讓我帶你回來成為兄弟吧！
(Hark!)
聽著吧！
(Behold!)
看著吧！
(My soul fights in the falling leaves)
我的靈魂如松葉紛飛
(l am Mouna Rudo)
我是莫那魯道
(l bring home the innocent souls)
而如今提領著無邪的魂魄回來了…
(Young warriors)
年輕的勇士啊…
(No one can defeat us)
沒人能抵抗我們！
(Oh, our warriors)
我們的勇士啊…
(much like the budding pine leaves)
像松枝嫩芽般的勇士啊…
You don't think I know
what you men are up to, do you?
你以為我看不出來…
你們男人在計畫什麼？
I'm the chief's daughter
我是頭目的女兒…
Wherever you're going
the children and I will follow
不管你將來去哪裡
我和孩子一定都要在你身邊
Your job is to guard this firepan
and keep the fire burning
你儘管守好火盆，別讓火熄了
When it's time to leave
I'll take you along with me
該離開的時侯，我不會丟下你們…
Yamada!
山田…
Sugiura, get out of there!
衫浦…你給我出來…
Come on, coward
-Who is it? What's going on?
-膽小鬼出來…
-是誰？怎麼了？
What's going on?
怎麼回事？
Stop! Who is it?
你住手…誰啊？
Baso, what the hell?
巴索…你在搞什麼？
What the hell are you doing?
Are you out of your mind?
你到底在幹什麼？你想死啊！
Shut up!
閉嘴！
(Do you know who l am?)
知道我是誰嗎？
(l'm Tado Mouna, a true warrior)
我是達多莫那！真正的勇士！
(When you bleed, the animosity)
(between you and me no longer exists)
當你流出血，你我的仇恨從此消失…
(l'm a true warrior)
我就是真正的勇士
(l'm a Seediq Bale, a true warrior)
我是賽德克巴萊，真正的勇士
(Your soul is welcome to dwell with me)
歡迎你的靈魂居住在我這裡
(l'll feed you with millet wine and foods)
我會拿酒及食物供養你
(There's no longer hatred between us)
我們之間不再有仇恨
(When you bleed, the animosity)
(between you and me no longer exists)
當你流出血，你我的仇恨從此消失…
(You'll be with our ancestors' spirits)
你也要和我們的祖靈一起
(to watch over my people)
守護我們族人…
Lubi, keep the fire burning
露比，別讓火熄了…
I'll be home before dark
我天黑就回來…
Women! Children! Why aren't you singing?
女人呀！孩子呀！
為什麼不唱歌呢？
Sing!
唱歌啊…
唱歌啊！
Mouna!
莫那…
My old friend!
我的老朋友！
Mouna! Chief Mouna!
莫那…莫那頭目…
Shut up!
閉嘴…閉嘴！
Not you
我不是在說你…
Tanah, split your men into two teams
達那哈…
把你們的人分成兩隊
You lead one team along Bkasan River
to annihilate all the police stations
你帶一隊沿著布砍散溪
消滅所有沿線的駐在所
and cut off the communication
of the Japanese to the east
切斷日本人東邊的聯絡線
The other team follows me to Gungu Clan
to meet up with other clans
另一隊跟我一起到荷戈社…
和其他部落會合！
What do we do
after those police stations are annihilated?
那我們消滅了那些駐在所之後呢？
After that? Come to Mehebu Clan for a drink
之後？…到我馬赫坡來喝酒！
Chief Mouna!
莫那頭目！
Where are they? Aren't they here yet?
人呢？都到嗎？
They're all here
都到了…
but Chief Dahdo doesn't allow
our Gungu Clan to join in the battle
但是塔道頭目不准我們荷戈社參戰
Everyone's trying to convince him
大家都在勸塔道頭目！
Have all the police stations been annihilated?
駐在所打下來沒有？
We've burned down every one of them
都燒光了！
Then why waste our time persuading him?
那還跟他囉嗦什麼！
I said no
不行就是不行…
Our clan is big. We must join in
我們這麼大的部落怎麼可以不參戰
Chief Dahdo..
塔道頭目…
even a boar fights back when driven to bay
Why don't you understand?
山豬都懂得反擊，為什麼你不懂？
I'd rather be punished by the Japanese
than have our whole clan wiped out
我寧可被日本人處罰，也不能滅族
My children, don't you remember
how your fathers died?
你們這些孩子…
忘了你們父親是怎麼死去的嗎？
No one from our Gungu Clan is allowed to go
我荷戈社任何一個人都不准參加！
Are you frightened to death by the Japanese?
Or are you spoiled by them?
你到底是被日本人嚇壞了？
還是被日本人給慣壞了？
Chief! Chief Mouna!
頭目…莫那頭目…
You know well
that we're bound to lose this battle
你明明知道這一戰一定會輸
Why do you insist on fighting it?
為什麼還要打？
Because of our ancestral spirit
that's soon to be forgotten
為了快被遺忘的圖騰！
Look at these young men
你看這些年輕人
Their faces are clean without the Seediq tattoos
白白淨淨的臉…
沒有賽德克該有的圖騰
Do you want to see their souls
forsaken by our ancestors' spirits?
你忍心看著他們死去的靈魂
被祖靈遺棄？
Or don't you think they're qualified
還是你覺得他們不夠資格
to be Seediq Bale
with hands stained with blood?
成為一個雙手染血的賽德克巴萊？
Ancestral spirit?
圖騰？
Ancestral spirit!
圖騰！
You want to sacrifice their lives
in exchange for these tattoos
拿生命來換圖騰印記…
but what does it take to get
these young lives back?
那拿什麼來換回這些年輕的生命？
Pride!
驕傲！
Let's go!
出發！
Mr. Inspector, look! Here comes the mist!
督學先生…
你看，起霧了！
What a beautiful sight!
好美呀！
Here comes your brother. Good luck!
哥哥來了…加油…
Good luck!
加油！加油！
What a thick mist!
好濃的霧啊！
Yeah, it's often misty around here
是啊！這裡的天氣一向如此
But with a mist so thick
how will they judge the games?
可是這麼濃的霧…
待會怎麼判定比賽成績啊？
Those games are just for kids
Having fun is all that matters
小孩子的遊戲好玩就好了…
Come on, have more hot tea. It's chilly
來…再來杯熱茶，天氣冷…
Thank you
謝謝…
We still have time for a rest
還有點時間的…可以再休息一下！
Be careful! -I'm sorry
小心！
對不起…
Are you alright? -Yeah, thank you
沒事吧？
嗯…謝謝！
Let's do it. There's no turning back
行動吧！已經脫不了身了！
My children..
孩子們…
at the other end of the rainbow
in the heavenly home of our ancestors
在通往祖靈之家的彩虹彼端
lies a fertile hunting ground
還有一座肥美的獵場
Our ancestors are all there
我們的祖先可都在那兒哪！
Only brave souls are allowed to enter
那片只有英勇靈魂才能進入的獵場
It's the one hunting ground
we cannot afford to lose
絕對不能失去…
Fellow tribesmen!
族人啊…
My fellow tribesmen!
Let's hunt the heads of our enemies
我的族人啊！
獵取敵人的首級吧！
We can no longer keep the hunting ground
in the Wushe mountains
霧社高山的獵場我們是守不住了…
Let's wash our souls clean with blood
用鮮血洗淨靈魂！
Stride over the rainbow
to our eternal hunting ground
走進彩虹！永遠的獵場！
We're offering a blood sacrifice to our ancestors
這是在血祭祖靈…
Young men, let our ancestors' spirits
be possessed in your blades
年輕人…
讓祖靈寄居在你們的刀鋒中
Entrust your hatred to the clouds and mists
把你們的仇恨寄存在雲霧間
Let's do it
行動吧！
Be still! How many times do I have to tell you?
排個隊動來動去
要講幾次才會明白啊！
Go to the back of the line!
排到最後去！
No, it's not what you think
…其實不是這樣的…
Hello?
喂…
Really?
真的嗎？
How fair-spoken you are!
-No, you're too kind
你真是會說話啊！
沒有…沒什麼啦！
Hatsuko!
初子…
What the hell! Lower you voice
幹什麼啊？那麼大聲…
Hanaoka?
花岡…
It's your shift at the ammunition storage
彈藥庫叫你去換班了！
Hello
你好！
Your candies
這是你的糖…
Thank you
謝謝囉…
謝謝你喔！
Hanako!
花子！
Hello -Hello
-你好！
Wow! You bought candies
你買糖果啦？
So cute
好可愛喔…
Come on, let's go. Bye!
我們也走吧…再見！
Bye!
慢走！
It's Ichiro!
一郎耶！
Welcome! You've come a long way
歡迎你來！辛苦你了！
This way please -Thank you
-請走這邊…
-謝謝！
It's spectacular
好盛大的運動會啊…
All rise!
起立！
Be quiet!
安靜！
Sing the national anthem
唱國歌！
(Our Mikado rules the world)
吾皇禦世…
(For generations to come)
千秋萬代永存…
(Like sands accumulating to rocks)
猶如小石成岩…
Get him!
抓住他！
Stop!
不要跑！
不要逃！
What's going on?
發生什麼事啊？
Keep playing! Come on!
繼續彈…繼續啊…
Sing! Keep singing!
唱歌…繼續唱歌…
Keep singing!
繼續唱歌啊…
Play it!
快點彈…
Keep singing!
繼續唱歌…
(Like sands accumulating to rocks)
猶如小石成岩…
Get him!
抓住他！
Here comes the blood sacrifice!
血祭祖靈了！
Come on!
走…
Run! Come on!
快逃！快逃呀！
Hatsuko! Hatsuko!
初子…初子…
Hatsuko!
初子…
Come on! Unlock the storage
The savages are hunting heads
快！打開槍庫，蕃人出草…
Hanaoka!
花岡…
Unlock that one too!
快把那間也打開！
Chief Mouna, my wife Obing
is still dressed in kimono
莫那頭目…
我妻子歐嬪還穿著和服…
Shut up! Open the door!
閉嘴！去開門…
Run for your lives!
你們快逃！
I'm a descendant from a samurai as well
我也是武士的後裔呀…
Mr. Satsuka! -Mr. Commissioner!
-佐塚先生…
-郡守…
Mr. Satsuka! -Come on!
-佐塚先生…
-快一點啊…
Mr. Satsuka!
佐塚先生…
Hide in there! Be quiet!
快進去…安靜點…
Hush! Be quiet!
小聲一點不要出聲…
Aren't you a savage too?
Why are you hiding with us?
你不也是蕃人嗎？
幹嘛也跟我們一起躲？
We're offering blood sacrifice
What are you daydreaming for?
血祭祖靈了…發什麼呆呀！
Follow me!
跟我走！
Pawan! Pawan!
巴萬…
Come on! Hurry up!
快…快一點…
Missed! Come on!
沒中…快！
Damned Japanese! I'll make you weep!
可惡的日本人，看我今天讓你哭…
Come with me!
跟我走！
(Oh, my children, l know)
(我的孩子啊，我知道)
(ln those passionate days)
(在那激情奔放的日子裡
(You've learned a song)
(你們學會一首歌)
(To sing for the soon-be-forgotten ancestral spirit)
(為即將被遺忘的祖靈唱歌)
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
My children! What are you doing?
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
孩子啊！你們在做什麼？
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
What on earth are you doing, my children?
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
我的孩子啊，你們在做什麼？
(Every note tightly embraces
our ancestors' spirits)
(每一個音符緊密地擁抱祖靈)
(Your dynamic bodies
dance to our ancestors' spirits)
(你們躍動的身軀舞向祖靈靈)
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
Dahdo! Dahdo!
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
塔道…塔道…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
Go to the school right now
to save your daughter Obing
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
快去公學校救你女兒歐嬪…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
She's dressed in kimono
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
她穿著和服哪！
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
No! No!
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
不要…不要…
(The pride of your souls
is like lightning in the clouds)
(你們靈魂的尊嚴像密雲中的閃電)
(No enemy dares to gaze at it)
(令敵人不敢直視)
Didn't we agree not to kill the Hans?
不是說別殺漢人嗎？
(But my children!)
What are you chasing him for?
-We did?
(But my children!)
Didn't we agree not to kill the Hans?
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
不是說別殺漢人嗎？
你還追什麼？…
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
有說過嗎？
(But my children!)
You'd better stay sober today!
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
你今天給我清醒一點！
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
(But my children!)
(但是，我的孩子啊？)
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
Don't throw anything hard stuff at me again!
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
下次別拿那硬硬的丟我…
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
Okay, fine
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
好好…
(The distant stars are nowhere to be seen)
(Your hatred darkens the heaven and the earth)
(你們的恨意讓天地暗下來)
(看不見遠方的星辰)
(The distant stars are nowhere to be seen)
Hush! Hush!
(看不見遠方的星辰)
安靜！安靜！
(Oh, see how the stars are dimming)
Hush! Hush!
(啊，那些星辰已漸漸垂滅)
安靜！安靜！
(Oh, see how the stars are dimming)
(啊，那些星辰已漸漸垂滅)
(My children!)
(我的孩子啊！)
(The chilling light reflected
off the tips of your machetes)
(你們刀尖的寒光)
(Makes the moon seem pale as wax )
(讓月亮蒼白如蠟
(The bloodstain on the tips of your machetes)
(你們刀尖的血漬)
Come on, Mr. Commissioner!
-I can't run anymore
(你們刀尖的血漬)
郡守，快點…
我跑不動了…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
What are you talking about? Come on!
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
你在說什麼…
快點…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
Get up!
起來…
(Keeps the night fire burning bright)
(讓夜晚不停燃燒)
Someone's here!
有人追過來了…
(Listen, children!)
Someone's here!
(聽啊，孩子們)
有人追過來了…
(Listen, children!)
I'm exhausted -This way!
Someone's here!
(聽啊，孩子們)
-我不行了…
-往這邊…這邊下去！
(Listen, children!)
I really can't run anymore!
(聽啊，孩子們)
我真的不行了…
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
Mr. Kikukawa!
菊川先生…
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
I don't want to die here!
我不要死在這裡呀…
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
Tado, don't shoot!
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
達多，別開槍！
(The sound drifting down from the forest)
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
(從森林裡飄落下來的聲音)
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
(ls it the sigh of our ancestors' spirits?)
Temu,
you'd do anything to become a hero, huh?
(是祖靈的嘆息)
泰牧，你想當英雄想瘋了…
(ls it the sigh of our ancestors' spirits?)
(是祖靈的嘆息)
Look, I killed a high-ranking official
你看，我殺的可是大官哪！
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
Look, I killed a high-ranking official
(還是風的嘆息)
你看，我殺的可是大官哪！
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
(還是風的嘆息)
Where's the other one?
還有一個呢？
(Or is it the sigh of the wind?)
(還是風的嘆息)
(Listen, children!)
(聽啊，孩子們)
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
Pihu..
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
比荷…
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
Don't kill me. We're friends
-My friend..
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
不要殺我…我們是朋友…
我的朋友…
(That sobbing flowing down
the Jhuoshuei River)
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
(從濁水溪流下來的嗚咽)
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
(ls it our ancestors' spirits weeping?)
I'm not killing people
I'm offering blood sacrifice to our ancestors
(是祖靈的哭泣)
我不是在殺人，我是在血祭祖靈…
(ls it our ancestors' spirits weeping?)
(是祖靈的哭泣)
(Or is it the clouds crying?)
(還是雲的哭泣)
Is that your teacher?
你們老師嗎？
(Or is it the clouds crying?)
(還是雲的哭泣)
(Oh, my children!)
(我的孩子啊！)
Teacher...My dear teacher..
老師…親愛的老師！
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
You think we're a bunch of cowards?
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
你以為我們很好欺負嗎？
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
I'm sorry. I was trying to educate you
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
對不起！我是在教育你們…
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
I'd punish a Japanese kid
when he makes mistakes
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
日本小孩犯錯我也有打呀！
(Look! The reddened earth is silent)
But you've been so mean to me!
(Look! The world keeps shivering)
(你們看，世界在不停地顫抖)
可是你打我最兇！
(你們看，染紅的土地沈默不語)
(Look! The reddened earth is silent)
(Look! The bark of Pusu Qhuni is peeling off)
(你們看，波索康夫尼的樹皮一片片剝落)
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
You poor Japanese..
可憐的日本人…
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
Come to the heavenly home of our ancestors
and be our friends forever
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
一起到我們祖靈的天家
當永遠的朋友吧！
(Touch your bloodstained hands)
(你們摸摸看，你們染血的雙手)
(Can they still hold the sand
from our hunting grounds?)
(還能捧住獵場的沙土嗎？)
(Touch your angry forehead)
(你們摸摸看，你們悲憤的前額)
(Can a beautiful rainbow bridge
still be spread out over it?)
(還能展開一座美麗的彩虹橋嗎？)
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
Come here! You go there!
過來這裡…你們去那邊！
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
Come here!
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
你過來！
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
Wait!
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
慢著…
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
Have you seen my daughter Obing?
有沒有看到我們家歐嬪？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
No
(Touch your uneasy mouth)
(你們摸摸看，你們疑惑不安的嘴
沒有…
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
Han...I'm a Han! -Go there!
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
漢人…我是漢人…
去那邊！
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
Have you seen my daughter Obing?
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
有沒有看到我們家歐嬪？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Are you a Seediq from Toda?
你是道澤人？
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Get lost!
你們走開…
(Can it still speak in all four seasons?)
(還能在所有的季節說話嗎？)
Tell your chief Temu Walis
回去告訴鐵木瓦力斯
that we're offering blood sacrifice
to our Seediq ancestors
這是血祭整個賽德克的祖靈
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Wushe has fallen into our hands
we Seediqs from Tgdaya
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
that we're offering blood sacrifice
to our Seediq ancestors
(我的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
這是血祭整個賽德克的祖靈
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
霧社已經被我們攻下來了
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Those of you from Toda and Truku
should join us as well
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
叫你們道澤和托洛庫也一起加入！
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
Move over!
過去！過去…
(All the pinecones have broken in the wind)
Move over!
(森林中的松子已在風中全部碎裂)
過去！過去…
(All the pinecones have broken in the wind)
(森林中的松子已在風中全部碎裂)
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
Chief Mouna?
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
莫那頭目
(The teary moon stops you
from walking towards death)
(淚光閃閃的月亮橫在你們走向死亡的途中)
(The gloomy clouds cannot shelter the sadness)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…歐嬪…
(The gloomy clouds cannot shelter the sadness)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing!
(暗鬱的雲朵已遮不住)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
歐嬪…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Jiro!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
二郎…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
Obing! -Jiro!
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
-歐嬪…
-二郎…
(that's sailing towards the dim starlight)
(向著微弱的星光緩緩駛去的悲傷)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Obing! -I'm in here!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
歐嬪…
我在這裡…
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Obing! -Help me!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
-歐嬪…
-快點救我…
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
Move away!
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
讓開！
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
Father!
父親…
(Time is light as a flame)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
(時間輕如一朵火焰
(Time is light as a flame)
Father!
(時間輕如一朵火焰
父親…
(Time is light as a flame)
Why must you hunt heads?
(時間輕如一朵火焰
為什麼要出草…
(That lights up the stars in your souls)
Why must you hunt heads?
(你們靈魂裡的星星已被點燃)
為什麼要出草…
(That lights up the stars in your souls)
(你們靈魂裡的星星已被點燃)
(Your dreams are vast like a blue ocean)
(你們夢廣大如一片藍色海洋)
(But the joyous tears
in your souls have dried out)
(而你們的靈魂裡歡樂的淚水卻已乾涸)
(Oh, my children! Do you know?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們知道嗎？)
(How much pain do you swallow to
sing the song of our ancestral spirit?)
(為唱出祖靈的歌需要吞下許多痛苦)
(How much shame do you swallow
to speak what you want to say?)
(為說出自己的話需要吞下許多屈辱)
(How much regret do you swallow
to fulfill your dreams?)
(為實現夢想需要吞下許多遺憾)
(Oh, children! What's wrong with you?)
(孩子啊，你們怎麼了？)
(Oh, my children!
What exactly is wrong with you?)
(我的的孩子啊，你們到底怎麼了？)